<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Document Store on Hervé Kakiang&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://hrv2k.github.io/tags/document-store/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Document Store on Hervé Kakiang&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 20019–2021, Hervé Kakiang; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 15:14:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hrv2k.github.io/tags/document-store/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Create a NoSQL Database Using MySQL Document Store</title>
      <link>https://hrv2k.github.io/post/create-a-nosql-database-using-mysql-document-store/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 15:14:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hrv2k.github.io/post/create-a-nosql-database-using-mysql-document-store/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;sql--nosql--mysql&#34;&gt;SQL + NoSQL = MySQL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysql.com/&#34;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt;, the world’s most popular database
management system (DBMS) has been rightfully used purely to create and
manage relational databases until recently.
During the last  decade, due to the requirements to store large quantities
of diverse data, we&#39;ve seen the rise in adoption and usage of NoSQL
databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/relnotes/mysql/5.7/en/news-5-7-12.html&#34;&gt;MySQL version 5.7.12&lt;/a&gt;,
MySQL Document Store was introduced, enabling MySQL to act as a NoSQL
JSON Document Store. MySQL is thereby both a relational and a NoSQL DBMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though there are many types of NoSQL databases with varying features,
they have all steered clear of the relational data model and are all
schemaless by definition.
There are mainly four categories of NoSQL databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key-value Pair NoSQL DB&lt;/strong&gt;: They store data in key/value pairs.
For instance, Amazon&#39;s Dynamo and Redis are in this category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Column or wide column NoSQL DB&lt;/strong&gt;: In column-based NoSQL databases,
columns don&#39;t have to be consistent across records. You can add columns
to specific rows without having to add them to every single record.
Google&#39;s BigTable, Apache Cassandra are examples of column-based databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graph-Based NoSQL DB&lt;/strong&gt;: They store data as well the relations amongst
them. This model is based on graph theory where structures are composed
of vertices and edges. An entity is stored as a node (vertex) with the
relationship as edges.
Neo4J, Infinite Graph, OrientDB, FlockDB are some examples graph-based
databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally &lt;strong&gt;Document-based NoSQL DB&lt;/strong&gt;: They store data as documents
using JSON or XML formats.
Amazon SimpleDB, CouchDB, MongoDB, are examples of popular document-based
NoSQL DBMS. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/document-store.html&#34;&gt;MySQL Document Store&lt;/a&gt;
belongs to this last category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advent of MySQL Document Store starts with the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/json.html&#34;&gt;support for native JSON data type in MySQL 5.7.8&lt;/a&gt;.
This feature enables efficient access to JSON documents stored in MySQL
databases. On top of this feature, MySQL Document Store was built, a pure
document store solution and was introduced in &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/relnotes/mysql/5.7/en/news-5-7-12.html&#34;&gt;MySQL 5.7.12&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently when you&#39;re considering database solutions, you are forced to
make a choice or combine multiple solutions – SQL/NoSQL,
Relational/Document Store. MySQL folks thought why not build both into
MySQL database. SQL and NoSQL build into one solution.
Hence &lt;strong&gt;SQL + NoSQL = MySQL&lt;/strong&gt;...?? They are not only built into the database
storage, but across all levels for the database stack – storage,
structure, protocol, APIs, Tools, etc.
And that’s what has been materialized with the release of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;X Plugin in MySQL 5.7.12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;X Dev API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL connectors: Connector/C++, Connector/Java, Connector/Node.js,  Connector/NET, Connector/Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL Shell: provides implementations of X DevAPI in JavaScript and Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this 2-in-1 solution, you can have both schemaless and schema data
models in the same technology stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://hrv2k.github.io/images/mysql_doc_store/nosql_sql_mysql.png&#34; alt=&#34;SQL + NoSQL = MySQL&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;x-protocol-x-plugin-and-x-devapi&#34;&gt;X Protocol, X Plugin, and X DevAPI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;x-protocol&#34;&gt;X Protocol&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MySQL has introduced a new protocol called X Protocol, which is used for
communications between MySQL Clients and a MySQL Server. It is based on
Google Protocol Buffers and supports asynchronous communication to the
server. The X Protocol is optimized for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/glossary.html#glos_crud&#34;&gt;CRUD&lt;/a&gt; as well as SQL API operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;x-plugin&#34;&gt;X Plugin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X Plugin is the MySQL Server plugin which enables client/server communication
using the X Protocol. It enables you to use MySQL as a document store.
Clients that implement X DevAPI, in other support the X Protocol, can
communicate with MySQL server and issue CRUD requests and send to and
receive JSON from the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To verify that X Plugin is installed on an instance of MySQL server
using MySQL Client, run the following command to to view the plugins list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;mysql -u user -p -e &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;SHOW plugins&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;x-devapi&#34;&gt;X DevAPI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The X DevAPI is a new, modern, async developer API for CRUD and SQL
operations, built on several technologies including the X Protocol enabled
through the X Plugin on top of X Protocol. It wraps powerful concepts in a simple
API (such as collections, tables, SQL operations). It can be used to make
non-blocking, asynchronous calls that follow common host language patterns.
It introduces Collections as new schema objects which is the basis for
MySQL document store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the developer or application&#39;s perspective, the X DevAPI is an the
API that (among other things) allows you to develop NoSQL solutions for
MySQL and use MySQL as a document store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-mysql-as-a-document-store&#34;&gt;Using MySQL as a document store&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To interface with MySQL as a document store, you need to have X Plugin
installed on MySQL server.
If you are using MySQL 8, X Plugin is enabled by default in MySQL 8.
Otherwise you have to install or upgrade to MySQL 5.7.12 or higher, then
follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/document-store-setting-up.html&#34;&gt;this guide to set up MySQL as a document store&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&#39;t use the old MySQL command-line client  to connect to MySQL as a
document store, since it doesn&#39;t implement the X Protocol. You need
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/mysql-shell/8.0/en/&#34;&gt;MySQL Shell&lt;/a&gt;.
MySQL Shell is the new modern and advanced command-line client for MySQL.
It is a unified scripting interface to MySQL Server. It supports scripting
in JavaScript and Python. It can also operate in pure SQL mode.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.mysql.com/doc/mysql-shell/8.0/en/mysql-shell-install.html&#34;&gt;Install MySQL Shell&lt;/a&gt;
and login to the local MySQL server using the root user using the following
command; enter the root password when prompted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ln&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;mysqlsh root@localhost&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
