<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cloud on Hervé Kakiang&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://hrv2k.github.io/categories/cloud/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cloud on Hervé Kakiang&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 20019–2021, Hervé Kakiang; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 12:27:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hrv2k.github.io/categories/cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>IBM Cloud Offerings with no expiration and no credit card required</title>
      <link>https://hrv2k.github.io/post/ibm-cloud-free-tier/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 12:27:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hrv2k.github.io/post/ibm-cloud-free-tier/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;h2 id=&#34;paas&#34;&gt;Paas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Foundry&lt;/strong&gt; is a Platform-as-a-service (PaaS) that enables you to deploy and
scale apps without managing server. Quota 256 MB of storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;storage&#34;&gt;Storage:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Object Storage&lt;/strong&gt; provides flexible, cost-effective storage for unstructured data.
You can use up to 25 GB per month for free under this offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;database&#34;&gt;Database:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloudant&lt;/strong&gt; is a scalable JSON document database for web, mobile, IoT and serverless
applications. You can store 1 GB of data in IBM Cloudant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Db2 on Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; is a fully managed cloud SQL database with a turbo-charged Db2 engine.
Under this offering, the quota is capped at 100 MB of data storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;devops&#34;&gt;DevOps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Availability Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; enables you to ensure applications are always
available and meeting user expectations for response time. Quota for this offering:
3 million data points per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Continuous Delivery&lt;/strong&gt; provides the support for DevOps best practices by using
Git, issue tracking, CI/CD pipelines and the Eclipse Orion Web IDE in the cloud. The quota
500 delivery pipeline jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Container Registry&lt;/strong&gt; manages Docker container images in a fully managed private
registry. Quota 5 GB per month pull data transfer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;security&#34;&gt;Security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Activity Tracker&lt;/strong&gt; enables you to gain insights about your users and their
applications with IBM Cloud services. Under this offerring you can inspect the 100,000
most recent cloud activity events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud App ID&lt;/strong&gt; adds authentication to your mobile and web apps, and protect your APIs
and back ends running on IBM Cloud. The quota 1,000 monthly events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;analytics&#34;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Cloud Analytics Engine&lt;/strong&gt; helps you develop and deploy analytics applications using
open source Apache Spark and Apache Hadoop. The quota 50 node hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IBM Streams&lt;/strong&gt; ingest, analyze, monitor and correlate data as it arrives from real-time
data sources. Quota 1 dedicated application resource&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
